Inventory of the International Association for the Evaluation of Educational Achievement Records, 1959-1992
Hoover Institution Archives
International Association for the Evaluation of Educational Achievement Records
1959-1992
86022
International Association for the Evaluation of Educational Achievement
552 manuscript boxes, 17 oversize boxes, 1 card file box, and 28 cubic foot boxes (256 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Reports, memoranda, correspondence, studies, questionnaires, tests, statistics, financial records, photographs, and sound recordings, relating to comparative education in various countries and to methods of measurement of educational attainment.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is stored off-site. It may be possible to have a limited number of boxes brought to the archives reading room for examination. A minimum of two days notice is required. Please contact the Hoover Institution Archives for further information.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Historical Note
The International Association for the Evaluation of Educational Achievement Records (IEA) is a non-profit, private association that conducts international comparative studies on schools and aids the research community in developing international tests and statistical techniques. The IEA has 39 member countries. Policy makers and educators use IEA data to assess alternative curricula, monitor the quality of schooling worldwide, identify effective schools and determine ways of improving their own educational systems, and improve their understanding of the instructional learning process. The organizational structure of IEA consists of a chairperson, general assembly, six-member standing committee, and secretariat. Specific studies are managed by specially appointed steering committees and implemented by national centers. IEA studies include a decennial assessment of a core of school studies in math, science, reading literacy, composition, and foreign languages. Other studies include: a 35-country reading literacy study; the third international mathematics and science study; school and teacher resource assessments that focus on opportunity-to-learn indicators; longitudinal and in-depth case studies; a 21-country computer education study; and a 13-country study of pre-primary early childhood care and education. In the area of information dissemination, the IEA publishes bulletins, a semiannual newsletter, and a guidebook on the IEA research network; the IEA also sponsors conferences on issue-related topics.(ERIC Digest http://www.ericdigests.org/pre-9218/international.htm)
For additional information, please see the IEA website at: http://www.iea.nl/
Scope and Content of Collection
Reports, memoranda, correspondence, studies, questionnaires, tests, statistics, financial records, photographs, and sound recordings, relating to comparative education in various countries and to methods of measurement of educational attainment.
Access Points
Education.; Educational tests and measurements.; Comparative education.
Subject Study
Subjects
Science
Mathematics
Reading Comprehension
Literature
French as a Foreign Language
English as a Foreign Language
Civics Education
Participating Countries (in math, maybe others)
Australia
Belgium I (Flemish Speaking)
Belgium II (French Speaking)
Chile
England
Federal Republic of Germany
Finland
France
Hungary
India
Iran
Italy
Japan
Scotland
Sweden
Thailand
Netherlands
New Zealand
Poland
United States
Populations
10 year olds
14 year olds
Last year of full time secondary education
Collection Contents
- Letters about Word-Knowledge Test, Sep 1968; Memorandum about item analyses of pre-test items; Meetings of technical groups [India and Iran don't like the idea of bubble sheet] (Box 1)
- English as a foreign language, instructions for administrators (Box 1)
- English speaking test (Box 1)
- Different questionnaires - Learning English (Box 1)
- English - listening comprehension test (Box 1)
- IEA / M / 9 10 12 14: Basic and applied research proposal, submitted to the US Commissioner of Education. Total request: 415,000 $, for 48 months (4 years). Includes Intro - nature of IEA. Other documents: "Education Yield"; "IEA Publications"; "press release about the beginning of school's survey in 20 countries of educational achievements in six-subject areas" (Box 1)
- Letter about copies of proposed final English as a foreign language test. Date: November 17, 1969. [to: all national centers, all committee members and Prof Husen. Also includes instructions] (Box 2)
- Report of the exploratory committee on technical education (appendix V). Date: 1971. [Abstract: proposal to conduct study on vocational-technical education. The study will include: categorization of programs, knowledge, attitudes. Why International? In some countries, USA, the field is lagged and thus International study will provide alternative theories and practice, "highly desirable way the repertoire of available solutions"] (Box 2)
- Brief accompanying notes to student univariates; plotting distributions of corrected test scores (Box 2)
- General attitudes and descriptive scales (Box 2)
- Memorandums about errors in questionnaires (Box 2)
- Paper titled: "Statistics and Experimental Design" (Box 2)
- English as a foreign language - instructions for administrators (Box 2)
- English writing test (Box 3)
- English as a foreign language - Phase II, Stage 3. October 1970 (Box 3)
- Finish (Finland) Reading Comprehension Report (Box 3)
- Reading Comprehension Report - from different countries (Box 3)
- Documents in French, dated 1963 and 1965 (Box 3)
- English as a foreign language: materials, rationales (Box 3)
- English tests (writing and speaking): instructions to national centers. Scripts/Scoring Sheets (Box 4)
- Miscellaneous: December 1967 - December 1968: (Box 5)
- Application to AERA, Postlethwaite December 1967 (Box 5)
- IEA secretary: Margaret Sutton (Box 5)
- Atlantic Studies/Atlantic Institute (Box 5)
- Letter to Mr. Arnon Aviner (Humbug) (Box 5)
- Letter about meeting of experts on Educational Research - Toronto Canada 26-30 August 1968 (Box 5)
- Conference: "Education as a factor of accelerated economic development" 22/8-3/9-1966 Istanbul (Box 5)
- IEA memorandums 1973 and letters about meetings/conferences (Box 5)
- Day file - June 1974 (Box 5)
- Letter mentioning the Lake Mohonk report. Document with the IEA logo (1974) (Box 5)
- Day file - copies March 1975 - August 1975 (Box 5)
- Day file - copies September 1975 - December 1975 (Box 5)
- Selected Foundation Fellows (Box 6)
- Academic literature 1970s (Box 6)
- IEA had fellowship program sponsored by the Spencer Foundation. Lists of fellows are available. Program ended 1976/1977. Copy of paper titled: "The relevancy of the IEA research for Canada" (published in The Canadian Society for the Study of Education Newsletter, February 1977) (Box 6)
- Data processing decisions (Box 6)
- Notes from meetings on data processing 1973 (Box 6)
- Data processing [?something] grant (Box 6)
- Information about grant budget; Notes from meetings on data processing 1975 (Box 6)
- Selection of the overall findings of the IEA six-subject study - presented at conference - Harvard University, November 1973 (Box 7)
- The National case study: an empirical comparative study of Twenty Educational systems. Draft, October 1973 (Box 7)
- Large Scale Surveys In Developing Countries (Box 7)
- Policy making and the international studies in Educational Evaluation - William Platt (Box 7)
- Papers and speeches from the Harvard conference (Box 7)
- Student Questionnaires and math tests (Box 7)
- Literature, population II IV (Box 7)
- Literature, cross-over study (Box 7)
- Math study phase I (Box 8)
- Dividers for each country (Box 8)
- Draft: report of the pre-testing for the IEA, June 1963. [Few documents about the translation issues] (Box 8)
- Papers from Finland (Box 8)
- Letters from Israel about the "gap" between the math test and the local curriculum (Box 8)
- Math Syllabus (Box 8)
- Pre-Pilot Parent Questionnaire (Box 8)
- Dividers for each country (Box 8)
- Instruction manuals for administration (Box 9)
- Manual, modified for use in Australia. Also, Israeli Version, England, Scotland (Box 9)
- Math Study Phase I Tests (Box 9)
- Memorandum about the development of IEA (Box 9)
- Dividers for each country (Box 9)
- Comments on Stage I and II, School I, Teacher I (Box 9)
- Comments sent from different national centers (Box 9)
- Memorandums in French, dated 19 April 1974 (2 folders) (Box 10)
- International Curriculum Organization (IOC Ray Philips) (Box 10)
- Letter to Postletwaite (at the International Institute for Educational Planning IIEP) from MOE in Sri-Lanka saying they can't joint the organization due to its current members ["we should wait till the ICO is more representative than it is now..."] (Box 10)
- Letter from Educational Inquiry INC. (located at Los-Angeles, CA), document dated July 1973 (Box 10)
- Booklet of the IIEP 1972 (Box 10)
- Proposal for the IOC (Box 10)
- Committee meetings 1972 (travel arrangements and accommodation) (Box 10)
- Table(s): IEA meetings 1972-1973 - dates and places, with sub-folders for each committee (Box 10)
- Committee meetings (Box 10)
- Many different documents (letters, flight tickets etc') from 1969 and later, with sub-folders (Box 10)
- Article: Keeves (1968) in "The Australian Science Teachers Journal, 14(1), pp. 26-33 (Box 11)
- Teachers education, teacher behavior, teaching method (Box 11)
- Briefing meeting (Ray Phillips) (Box 11)
- Current grant-giving agencies: (Box 11)
- Six-Subjects: Ford foundation; Leverhulme; Volkswagen; USOE (Box 11)
- Riksbanken (Box 11)
- Exploratory Committees: Pre-school: Ford; Van-Leer; Primary reading: Ford; Motivation: Ford, UNESCO; Teacher Learning Strategies; Ford; Curriculum Planning: Ford; Fellowships: Spencer (Box 11)
- Science (Ray Phillips) (Box 11)
- Replies to the IEA science test, letters referring to the term "yield" or "educational yield". Most of the papers are from 1972/3 (Box 11)
- Literature by Roy Phillipps (study??) (Box 12)
- Letters, drafts and other documents from 1972 (Box 12)
- Teacher Behavior Study (Box 12)
- Proposal for an International Study on Teacher Behavior and Classroom Environment in Relation to Student Achievement. Date: October 1970 (Box 12)
- Document: Teacher Behavior - Review of The Literature, dated 1969 and prepared by Barak Rosenshine (Box 12)
- Correspondence and reaction letters to the proposal (Box 12)
- Teacher Behavior Conference (Box 13)
- Grant proposals for the conference: Russell-Sage, Rockefeller, Ford. Letters and memorandums about the proposal and nominations for participation from different countries (dated 1971) (Box 13)
- Teacher Behavior Replies to Documents (Box 13)
- Document by Barak Rosenshine in collaboration with Stanford and Columbia University. Includes folders for each country (Israel is not there). Documents (1968) about the Longitudinal Study - kind of a survey of all countries (USSR is also missing) (Box 13)
- Reading Comprehension - Roy Phillips (Box 13)
- Letters from 1973 regarding the reading comprehension test (Box 13)
- German Curriculum Seminar (Box 13)
- Documents from 1971 dealing with finance of seminar /meetings (Box 13)
- IEA fact-sheet (April 1970). Internal papers, charts and explanations. (Box 14)
- Symposium- Uppsala - April 6-8 1970 (Box 14)
- Special Hypo-Theses (1972): (Box 14)
- Social Bias [letters about the parents occupation measurements and the difficulty to compare between countries] (Box 14)
- Age of Entry [Postlethwaite writes to Thorndike: "Although I feel that we are on very shaky ground when undertaking between nation hypotheses I felt that certain of what Torsten calls the 'pervading hypotheses' undertaken in the math study should be repeated with the present data"] (Box 14)
- Future IEA meetings and follow up (June 1970): (Box 14)
- Proposal (1970): a cross national study if the process of decision making in the educational system. Minutes from different meetings (how to convey countries to support the IEA?). Document (1970): The International Association for the Evaluation of Educational Achievements (IEA) - Projects and Programs (Box 14)
- Minutes of the Technical Committee. Meeting in New-York, 17th June 1969 (Box 14)
- Day-File, October - December 1974, January - February 1975 (Box 14)
- Day-File, September 1973 (Box 15)
- Day-File, November 1973. Same, documents about computer programs. (Box 15)
- Day-File, December 1973 [seems that these are documents are about technical/methodological aspects] (Box 15)
- Day-File, January 1974 (Box 15)
- Reading Comprehension, population IV sub-test (Box 16)
- Reading Speed pre-test, with folders for each country (Box 16)
- Word Knowledge, with folders for each country (Box 16)
- Day-File, September 1973 (part II) (Box 16)
- Letters mentioning papers titled: "Competencies Represented By The International Association For The Evaluation Of Educational Achievements (IEA) And Their Implications For Future IEA Work (Box 16)
- Minutes of the Six-subject project review committee (few copies of the same document); Day-file copies (1979) (Box 16)
- Civic Education, population IV Sub-test A-E (Box 17)
- Civic Education, population I Sub-test A-C (Box 17)
- Civics - Germany, England, Sweden (Box 17)
- Civic Education, population IV Sub-test D-E (Box 18)
- Japanese Questionnaire Translation (Box 18)
- Math test - questionnaire, by countries (Box 18)
- Math - Tests (Box 19)
- Math - Tests (Box 20)
- English as a Foreign Language (Box 21)
- Math - Tests (Australia) (Box 22)
- Tapes (?) - Italy (Box 23)
- Tapes (?) - Italy (Box 24)
- English as a Foreign Language - Speaking Tests (Box 25)
- Some IEA/ TR documents I (Box 26)
- Mainly documents from 1971 dealing with methodological questions (Box 26)
- Some IEA/ TR documents II (Box 26)
- Mainly documents from 1971-1972 dealing with methodological questions (Box 26)
- Errata Sheets Blue (Box 26)
- Supplementary page to supplementary manual (Box 26)
- Miscellaneous- Phase I notes (Box 27)
- Tapes - Misc (Box 28)
- Tapes - Misc (Box 29)
- Erratum Sheets - misc (Box 30)
- All Subjects - International Subject Area Committees (Box 31)
- Miscellaneous, April-December 1967 (Box 32)
- Husen - Pidgeon, October 1965 (Box 32)
- Miscellaneous- all subjects - by language (Box 33)
- Math - Data processing issues (Box 34)
- Math (Maybe for all subjects) school, teacher, and students questionnaires (Box 35)
- Intellectual process, Foshay Evaluation meeting, June 5-10 1961 (Box 36)
- Paper slips in which scholars permit any member of our group to make scientific use of the results obtained in the scholar's country. [folder describes "the behind the scenes" of the first report] (Box 36)
- Intellectual process, Cobb, Foshay, Bulletin etc. [Seems to be questionnaires from France or Belgium (non-verbal test).] (Box 36)
- Reading Comprehension - Pretest, International Documents (Box 37)
- Reading Comprehension - Subtests (Box 38)
- United-States General Correspondence, October 1965 - April 1967, Phase II. Different documents and letters (Box 39)
- Articles by Non-IEA Members (Box 39)
- Proposal (1964) for the improvement and standardization of statistics for educational planning and policy in OECD countries. Label written in red pen: NOT FOR PUBLICATION (Box 39)
- Math - Phase I - Final (Box 40)
- Math - Phase I - Final (Box 41)
- French as a Foreign Language - Fluency Tests; Student Questionnaires (Box 42)
- French as a Foreign Language (Box 43)
- French as a Foreign Language (Box 44)
- English as a Foreign Language (Box 45)
- English as a Foreign Language - Report (Box 46)
- English as a Second Language (Box 47)
- File building: correspondence regarding computer programs (dates 1969) (Box 48)
- Folders with different forms and documents (Box 48)
- Correspondence With National Centers about punched cards (early 1970s) (Box 48)
- Correspondence on IEA brochure 1968. [A good way to learn about the organizational presentation of self and about the active members.] (Box 48)
- Letters send out to NTO's binder (Box 48)
- List of National optional items; Early IEA codebook (1972); [and 9 more folders] (Box 49)
- Correspondence on IEA brochure 1970 (Box 49)
- Civics - Rationale for Instrument, plus Miscellaneous on various countries (short - copy later) (Box 50)
- Letters and correspondence on printing (Box 51)
- National codes and codebooks (Box 51)
- Lists of computer files (Box 51)
- Folders with codes, computer programs, billing, computer programs etc (Box 51)
- Operations in IOWA (Box 52)
- IEA general, reliability measurements (Box 52)
- Other folders deal with punching cards, Iran coding system (Box 52)
- 1971, L-Z: Catalog of the International Association of Applied Psychology (1971, Liege) (Box 52)
- 1971, A-K: (Box 52)
- UNESCO Hamburg Documents, 1972 [provides UNESCO's perspective on the process] (Box 52)
- English as a Foreign Language - Proposed Final Test - Cognitive (Box 53)
- UNESCO Hamburg documents 1970 - 1971 (Box 54)
- "Skeeppenholm" Seminar 1970 (Box 54)
- Husen correspondence 1970 (Box 54)
- English as a Foreign Language - First Draft of Final Report (Box 55)
- English as a Foreign Language - Pretests (Box 56)
- Correspondence binder, 1970/1971 FOLEB? includes folders about seminar, memos etc (Box 57)
- New Proposals to Grant Giving Agencies: Federal Rep of Germany, Van Leer (Netherlands), Olivetti (Italy), ICI, Sloan, Spencer, Stone, Shell, OECD, Ford, early 1970s (Box 57)
- English as a Foreign Language - International Documents (Box 58)
- Civic Education correspondence countries. Comments and responses from different countries (Box 59)
- Materials from the Swedish Bored of Education (Box 59)
- Proposals for New Grants: Olivetti (1970); Spencer (1972); Boun-XXXX (Germany, 1970); SHELL (1971); SIDA (1972); Van-Leer (1973); Ford (1973); UNESCO (Box 60)
- USOE Quarterly Progress Report (inside it says that these are IEA quarterly progress report - February 1973 - May 1973 (Box 60)
- Civics - Meeting (looks good) (Box 61)
- Civic Education, correspondence committee (Box 62)
- Letters and documents, dates 1969 - early 1970s (Box 62)
- Civic Education binder, April 1970 (Box 62)
- Civics - National Documents (Box 63)
- Civics - Tests, Report (Box 64)
- Civics (Box 65)
- Civics (Box 66)
- French as a Foreign Language (Box 67)
- French as a Foreign Language, miscellaneous Correspondence (Box 68)
- Math - Drafts of French Version of Report (Box 69)
- Newsletter Vol. 3. Year - 1974. Folder contains Black and White pictures of central people and events (i.e. the Harvard meeting) (Box 70)
- Mailing list and other information (Box 70)
- Civic Education - Draft Monograph, 1st and 2nd versions and also comments (Box 71)
- Grant giving Agencies: Ford (1970) and Volkswagen (1973). A few letters show the financial issues (Box 71)
- Teaching Learning Strategies project, Proposal for International Study of Student Responses To Literature (Box 72)
- Motivation - International Documents (Box 73)
- French population I, II, IV re-test L, R. Mainly, computer outputs divided by countries (Box 74)
- SIDA, Kenya Science Teachers (1969, in Swedish) and questionnaires in English (Box 74)
- IEA Mathematics Study, lay version (1972) (Box 74)
- Stage 2, MRCD and punched cards, correspondence with national centers (1970) (Box 74)
- International Committee on Motivation (Box 75)
- French as a Foreign Language - Subtests - Populations I,II, and IV (Box 76)
- French as a Foreign Language - Item Analysis (Box 77)
- French as a Foreign Language - Re-tests - Populations I,II,IV, IVS (Box 78)
- English as a Foreign Language - Item Analysis by country- Population II (Box 79)
- English as a Foreign Language - Sub-test - Population II, IV (Box 80)
- International Committee for Learning Strategies (Box 81)
- International Committee on Primary Reading (Box 82)
- Pre-school Project, Primary Reading project proposal (Box 83)
- Report to the U.S. Office of Education on the (Box 84)
- Math Tests final versions - various levels (Box 85)
- Day Files - 1974 (Box 86)
- Day Files - 1973 - 1974 (Box 87)
- Day Files - 1974 (Box 88)
- International School - Hamburg - Questionnaires (Box 89)
- Bulletin no.2 (1963), several copies (Box 90)
- International Evaluation of Achievement Mathematics - Pilot Study 1963. [Seems to be national report from England and USA.] (Box 90)
- Variables With Differing National Categories (Box 90)
- Other envelopes include questionnaires from the Math test; paper titled: "social class, ability and school achievement in 12 countries (1968, given by Postlethwaite in University of Michigan), memorandums about the development of instruments, review of IEA Civic Education Pre-Tests, booklet titled "Suggested Hypothesis and Data Gathering Procedures for the IEA study (Box 90)
- Curriculum Training 1971 - Volume 2 (Box 91)
- Administration (Box 91)
- Science - Plus, 20 years of science education in Japan (Box 92)
- Math (Box 93)
- Discipline - in Japanese (Box 94)
- Math - Tests - Netherlands (Box 95)
- Math - Tests - Finland (Box 96)
- Math - Japanese National Report of (Box 97)
- Envelopes: reports to USOE - Chicago 1966-1967 (Box 98)
- Invoices and Accounting (Box 98)
- Data Bank Manuals (Box 99)
- folders for different countries: Poland, Thailand, Sweden, New Zealand (1971) (Box 99)
- Math (Box 100)
- French, English, Civics Education - data sheets (Box 101)
- Civics (Box 102)
- Civics (Box 103)
- Miscellaneous (Box 104)
- Science (Box 105)
- Miscellaneous (Box 106)
- Social Studies - Seminar, 1971 (Box 107)
- Seminar, 1971 (Box 108)
- Math - Italy - Summary of results (Box 109)
- Questionnaires and Frequencies (Box 110)
- GRANNA seminar 1971 Faculty (Box 110)
- GRANNA seminar 1971 materials (Box 111)
- Reading Comprehension correspondence (Box 111)
- Literature (Box 112)
- Literature (Box 113)
- Literature (Box 114)
- French as a foreign language - Tapes (Box 115)
- French as a foreign language - Tapes (Box 116)
- Curriculum Seminar GRANNA 1971: observers (Box 117)
- Curriculum Seminar 1971: countries not attending (Box 117)
- Curriculum Seminar GRANNA 1971 - end of seminar questionnaire and evaluation (Box 117)
- Curriculum Seminar GRANNA 1971: follow up correspondence (Box 118)
- Administration Volume II, papers from Curriculum Seminar GRANNA (Spain) and other hand-written documents (Box 118)
- Second Language Seminar 1971 (GRANNA?) (Box 118)
- Elementary Education Volume I (Box 119)
- Elementary Education Volume II [seems like reports from different countries] (Box 119)
- Second Language Seminar 1971 (GRANNA?) Volume III (Box 119)
- Invoices 1973 (Box 120)
- Invoices 1976 (Box 120)
- TAPES speaking French (Box 120)
- Civics - United States (Box 121)
- Civics (Box 122)
- Curriculum Seminar material (Box 123)
- Curriculum Training Seminar materials 1971 (Box 123)
- Miscellaneous correspondence 1973 (Box 124)
- Future of the IEA 1971 [Husen] and comments and correspondence to the document (Box 124)
- SIDA binder (Box 124)
- Miscellaneous correspondence 1972 A - M (Box 125)
- Miscellaneous correspondence 1972 M - Z (Box 125)